<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>PinkFalcon - Birds</title>
    <subtitle>Sometimes technical, sometimes about geese</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://pinkfalcon.ca/categories/birds/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://pinkfalcon.ca"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2024-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://pinkfalcon.ca/categories/birds/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>A Tale of Two (or more) Geese</title>
        <published>2024-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              prograhamer
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://pinkfalcon.ca/a-tale-of-two-or-more-geese/"/>
        <id>https://pinkfalcon.ca/a-tale-of-two-or-more-geese/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://pinkfalcon.ca/a-tale-of-two-or-more-geese/">&lt;p&gt;This all happened back in April this year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I held off on writing about this, because I wasn&#x27;t quite sure what to make of it. Enough time has passed, and I&#x27;m still not sure what happened exactly, but maybe that&#x27;s the interesting thing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was spending quite a lot fo time at my local conservation areas, as I talked about in a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&#x2F;vulture-photography&#x2F;&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. During one of my trips to take photographs, I saw something I&#x27;d never seen before: geese sitting on the cliff edge. It&#x27;s definitely not the first place I&#x27;d expect to see geese. There was one spot in particular, where there would always be a pair or just a single goose, every time I visited.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would sit for quite a while in that spot, enjoying the calm forest and watching the geese. It was a good tranquil place to sit, maybe that&#x27;s why the geese chose it? Hopefully I didn&#x27;t ruin the tranquility too much for them!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some time, one of the geese stood up to reveal a clutch of eggs it was incubating.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;



&lt;img
    class=&quot;article-block&quot;
    alt=&quot;A goose on a cliff edge. Its body is raised just enough to reveal eggs in a downy nest beneath it.&quot;
    srcset=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;cliff1.b9033bcfc3ea69d6.jpg 480w, https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;cliff1.0833e3a0e1bfd40b.jpg 800w, https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;cliff1.17e99e4838e1015a.jpg 1440w&quot;
    sizes=&quot;(max-width: 480px) 480px, (max-width: 800px) 800px, 1440px&quot;
    src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;cliff1.0833e3a0e1bfd40b.jpg&quot;
&#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So not only were these geese sitting on the cliff edge, but they were nesting here. I looked up Canada goose nesting habits, and found that they prefer to nest by or surrounded by water. So, not a cliff then. Reading more, it sounds like the female tends to stay with the eggs to incubate them, while the male stays near to stand guard. Maybe this explained why I&#x27;d sometimes see one goose, sometimes two, but one would always be sitting, and if there were two, the second would always be standing nearby.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;



&lt;img
    class=&quot;article-block&quot;
    alt=&quot;A goose standing guard, looking out from the cliff top.&quot;
    srcset=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;bruce1.455a748f0a841e74.jpg 480w, https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;bruce1.d94b647816a86396.jpg 800w, https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;bruce1.4603ac57f9c9615b.jpg 1440w&quot;
    sizes=&quot;(max-width: 480px) 480px, (max-width: 800px) 800px, 1440px&quot;
    src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;bruce1.d94b647816a86396.jpg&quot;
&#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent quite a lot of time with the geese.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then one day, I went to see them in their usual spot and they were gone. All that was left was some down and eggshell fragments.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feared the worst. Maybe an animal, perhaps a raccoon, had got to the eggs and the geese had abandoned the nest site?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks later, I went back to what had been their nest area and they were back! Or were they? I would say my ability to tell two Canada geese apart is pretty much non-existent.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still wonder about the story of these geese. Were there two couples, both using the same fairly secluded nesting site one after the other? Was it the same pair, and the first clutch met some unpleasant fate, so they rebuilt the nest a tried again?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking about what I&#x27;ve read about Canada goose nesting habits, it does sound like something went wrong with the first brood. According to an &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;birdfact.com&#x2F;articles&#x2F;Canada-goose-nesting&quot;&gt;article on birdfact.com&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, Canada geese will reuse the same nest site throughout their lives, and if a brood fails for some reason, they may attempt a second brood 14 to 20 days later. The timing of them returning in particular makes me wonder if something bad did happen to their first clutch of eggs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope if that&#x27;s the case, that their second brood was successful.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Bird Photography</title>
        <published>2024-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              prograhamer
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://pinkfalcon.ca/vulture-photography/"/>
        <id>https://pinkfalcon.ca/vulture-photography/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://pinkfalcon.ca/vulture-photography/">&lt;p&gt;For a couple of years now, I have been taking photographs of turkey vultures at some conservation areas relatively close to my home. At these conservation areas, there are cliffs, and you can often enjoy a view of the vultures soaring past at eye level and only 10-20m away.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had previously enjoyed photography, but had fallen out of the habit over the years, and this seemed like a good excuse to get back into it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find I still routinely struggle with relatively basic things:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bringing the camera to my &quot;good&quot; eye (for some reason I instinctively bring it to my weaker eye)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bringing the camera to my eye and having it pointing at what I was focused on with my eye (this is pretty easy with wider angles, but I find it tricky with longer focal lengths, especially when pointing in slightly the wrong direction means pointing at a featureless sky with no hint as to the direction to move)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;holding the camera steady&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tracking moving objects&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;focusing on objects (using wide apertures and long focal lengths means that the depth of field is tiny, and the focus is really sensitive)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to these more technical issues, I have found photographing birds also helps me work on my patience and awareness. These two things can make up for some of my shortcomings in the technical domain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last weekend, I got the one of the best pictures of a turkey vulture I think I have taken, and I believe this is more down to patience and getting into the patterns of the vultures than any skill improvement. It&#x27;s still flawed in a number of ways, but I will try to focus on the positive. I had previously taken reasonable static photos of vultures at rest, but I have really wanted to get a nice photo of them in flight.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will often sit or stand in an area that&#x27;s relatively exposed at the cliff edge and take photos of the vultures as they soar past. The trouble is, the closer they are, the faster they pass, and the more technical difficulty I have as I have to quickly react and adjust. So I have quite a lot of &quot;ok&quot; photos from a bit of a distance, but pretty much no good ones where the subject naturally occupies the majority of the frame, even at 300mm.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what was different this time? I saw a couple of vultures perched in a tree and I waited. It seemed unlikely for them to just stay there forever, so I just needed to be ready for when they took flight. This removed a load of time sensitivity - I could get ready with the exposure, focus, framing, etc. and I&#x27;d just need to keep the bird in frame as it leaves its perch.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also found as I spend more time with the vultures, they become more predictable to me. So I can be better prepared and less reactive when the opportunity for a photograph presents itself. So even when they are already in flight, I have more of a chance of taking a reasonable photo.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still want to work on all of the technical skills, to give myself the ability to quickly react and take pictures, but finding these strategies to make the most of the skills I currently have makes the experience less frustrating. Now I will take a hundred photos and be pretty happy with a couple of them at least.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some pictures:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;



&lt;img
    class=&quot;article-block&quot;
    alt=&quot;A turkey vulture flying, having just left its perch&quot;
    srcset=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;vulture001.1c17b663f49d6479.jpg 480w, https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;vulture001.885620c2e191372b.jpg 800w, https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;vulture001.c12e5d27457b01c5.jpg 1440w&quot;
    sizes=&quot;(max-width: 480px) 480px, (max-width: 800px) 800px, 1440px&quot;
    src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;vulture001.885620c2e191372b.jpg&quot;
&#x2F;&gt;



&lt;img
    class=&quot;article-block&quot;
    alt=&quot;A turkey vulture soars in from the right of the frame&quot;
    srcset=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;vulture002.76436d2ba33b34ee.jpg 480w, https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;vulture002.d6e948c9a61bdf55.jpg 800w, https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;vulture002.71b300a97aa63bbb.jpg 1440w&quot;
    sizes=&quot;(max-width: 480px) 480px, (max-width: 800px) 800px, 1440px&quot;
    src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;pinkfalcon.ca&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;vulture002.d6e948c9a61bdf55.jpg&quot;
&#x2F;&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
